this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant detailed
discussions about software engineering
topics at least once a month
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our website for supporting the
podcast
[Music]
welcome to a new show on software
engineering radio our topic is software
development in large a child settings my
guest today is best father and a
microphone is Michael bass is an HR
coach running his own company and is
very experienced in large a child
settings best why don't you introduce
yourself briefly and and best for them
I'm originally Dutch so originally from
close to where you are Michael I have
not lived there for a long time I now
live in Singapore I worked in a small
coaching company called Adi before that
about 10 years ago I still worked in
several smaller at that time the dot-com
companies in Holland and then I had
enough of living in Holland and I picked
my suitcase and moved to Beijing China I
where I joined a small company called
Nokia and in I lived for a year in
Beijing building a DSL equipment
software for a DSL equipment then I got
transferred to Hangzhou China where we
started working on large
third-generation network elements after
a couple of years I had the opportunity
to introduce agile iterative development
which was kind of what I was more used
to when living in Holland but we'll talk
about that later I had to move to
Finland so I moved to Finland and to
Helsinki where I ran and changed project
for agile iterative development on the
whole organization it was supposed to be
a pilot but it got out of hand and after
that after two years I decided to move
away from Finland
again because it's it's a very cold
place to live and I first moved to to
Hangzhou so back where I was to move
back to the old product to try to help
them adopt scrum on the whole product
just about 500 people and then after
then I moved to Singapore where it's
never cold and worked with my own
company called
Adi and now we offer a job coaching
mainly in Asia and we got a job Japan OD
Japan and Oddie China and we got some
people in Hong Kong also so it's going
pretty well
so you also wrote two books where you
collected and shared all your
experiences what do they focus on okay
so I wrote two books together with and a
good friend of mine
Craig lahrman and we have been working
together for for many years within a
Nokia and later on Nokia Siemens
Networks and so they're they're both
about scaling agile and lean development
and they're structured in such a way
that the first book is more conceptual
so it talks about we took the concept of
thinking tools from Don Reinard since
book on product development next-gen
forgot what it's called now and are the
product design not a design factor and
so it's the first half of the first book
is full of thinking tools such as
queueing theory systems thinking lean
thinking and it describes how to how to
think about the organization or how to
think about the development then the
second part of the first book we called
organizational tools and in the
organizational tools will describe how
to structure your organization one of
the key chapters there is the chapter on
feature teams which describes how you
can structure your organization in a
different way than traditional
organizations what the benefits of doing
that are and also what it drawbacks of
doing that are and then the last part of
the first book is a book called an
chapter called organization and it just
basically goes over all the
organizational issues that you will have
and gives advice on how you can change
your organization or or what kind of
what kind of things you might expect
when being in and being in an agile
transformation the second book is called
practices for lean and agile development
and as the title suggests it focuses on
practices so there's an for example a
chapter called test we decided to that
do test first so that's the first
chapter chapter called test which
describes how testing issues related to
adult development and specifically
focused on testing issues that are
common in in larger skill projects and
then it goes from test to design to
planning product management contracts so
the second book is structured around
topics of practices and then gifts tips
related to these practices both books
are organized around tips or experiments
where we suggest to try
something or to not do something and
they try to avoid making - let's see -
too much you must follow this one way
type of head lice so you mentioned that
you had the opportunity to start
iterative and basically a child
development was that something you were
looking for for a long time or how did
agility get started with you for me it
it started before before the agile
manifesto at that time which is a long
time ago at that time I was working with
an dot-com company in Holland and we
were kind of feeling uncomfortable that
we were not developing our products in
the way as we were taught and as all the
literature says the way we should be
doing it
we had been experimenting with CMM at
that time which was very new but it just
didn't fit well at all and at that point
the context first extreme programming
book was published and I got a copy of
that immediately and when we read
through it was like oh so we are not the
only person persons thinking that the
traditional way doesn't work and it
described a lot of practices which we
were already doing and then a couple of
practices which we hadn't been thinking
about very much at that time so we
started adopting some of these also
so my first agile experiences were
extreme programming experiences right
after around the period that the first
XP book was published
and at that time it was it was obvious
it was common knowledge that agile
development didn't work in enlarged
skill products it only worked for small
teams that would have been my next
question well some people still claim
that agility only works for for small
teams well that's a less than 10 less
than 20 people so why should the chilla
D work for large software development
teams with more for example more than
100 developers so at that time when I
got exposed to agile development it was
mainly about extreme programming but
then when I joined a large product of
hundreds of people I went back to the
traditional way of development since
everybody knows that agile development
doesn't work for large projects and I I
accepted that common knowledge at that
time so we try to get traditional
development to work and traditional
development also doesn't work for large
projects so it's not like you have to
choose between agile development that
doesn't work and traditional development
that works you have to choose between
agile development that was common
knowledge that didn't work and
traditional development that also didn't
work and we tried really really hard to
get it to work
in fact we wrote a couple of experience
reports on improving software
inspections which we were very very
active in because that was the only way
to get the the early feedback in a more
waterfall a cycle and and I think we we
got as far as we could with with
improving the traditional server
inspection process but it still didn't
work very well
so we already started piloting in
smaller teams
of the agile practices so when I had the
opportunity to to run this
organizational wide change process for
me it was going back to my roots it was
like I know this works I've done that
years ago I know the traditional
development doesn't work so let's just
try to get adult development to also
work on larger scale projects and at
that time there was nothing written or
known about agile development at large
field projects except for Ron Crocker's
Motorola project which was supposedly
going to be published in a book that it
never got published and that was about
all there was known about agile
development in large steel projects at
that time so why should it work on
large-scale projects the same reason why
it should work on small scale projects
there's not much difference I have
actually read a book by coppice Jones
titled software engineering best
practices and he makes the claim that
agility doesn't work for large software
teams and twice even to have a proof for
it well he says well you need to use the
team software process to be successful
in large development what what is your
experience with it well first of all
capers Jones has done and it's about one
of the only person providing reasonably
useful information from research-based
information in in our industry so
whatever he says I think we we should at
least take serious though my experiences
are are very much counter to to him
train I'm trying to prove that agile
wouldn't work on
large-scale severe development okay and
we'll get back to a TSP a little bit
later and I've been thinking about why
why the the data he and others collect
are suggesting that agile doesn't work
or that it doesn't happen on on
large-scale development and my easily
explain it by by looking at how slow
large products actually change like some
of the products we've been working on
they are they're already developed for
about twenty to thirty years and most of
their practices were copied from the
products that were developed before that
so making making change in large
products first of all takes a lot of
time you have to be really really
patient and second large products are
often risk avoidance in change so
there's just much less large products
who have tried to do agile development
and therefore if you would measure the
or research the the type of development
styles development methods used in
projects I bet at this moment it will
still be all small projects mainly use
agile development large project mainly
use waterfall development and so the
slowness of change and the slowness of
the feedback or the success cycle on
large products is how I would explain
capers research results though having
read part of his latest book I have to
say he does seem to have quite a lot of
misunderstandings of what scrum or agile
development actually is so part of
that might also be related to his own
misunderstandings anyway my experiences
are not that it doesn't work on large
product but the opposite that
traditional development doesn't work on
large products and agile development is
tough it's a big change but it works
better than a traditional development
when I read your books it's clear to
notice that you base your methodology
your recommendations on scrum so why did
why do you base unscramble what what
kind of benefits do you have from it I
think that goes back to to how we got
started
in in Nokia networks at that time we
believe very strongly that people and
projects should should choose their own
way of working and not to make an
organizational white agile process and
and deploy it or roll it out to the rest
of the organization and luckily we were
not in a position where we could even do
that because we were put in the
organization in a place where we had
absolutely no authority over any other
development organizations so what we did
how we started was we gave introductions
to agile development in general where we
would explain extreme programming
explain scrum explain feature driven
development crystal and other agile
methods and we would ask the development
groups which one would you like to try
out and most of the development groups
replied like well scrum that
that sounds pretty easy and I
extreme programming sounds like a to big
change it sounds too extreme but let's
let's try out scrum it sounds easy and
of course all of them after they started
all often realized that it's it's not
easy at all and it is a big change but
the the simplicity of scrum makes it a
really good starting point so at that
time we got started with scrum Mason
framework and then next to that promoted
the the technical practices which came
from from extreme programming and I
think that's the deep background how we
got started with scrum as a basis but
looking back scrum does provide the
structure you need to to be able to to
scale up agile development extreme
programming also provides that and in in
my opinion and good scrum team and a
good extreme programming team are the
same there's no difference if if a team
gets gets really good in agile
development it it doesn't really matter
anymore what what they call it but scrum
provided the the minimum framework that
was that was excellent and an excellent
basis for thinking about how to scale
their up which HL practices don't work
in large setups and ask the other way
around which are especially important I
don't think there's much practices that
that don't work in large skill
organizations or large skill development
and the reason is that some of the some
of the additional practices we use for
scaling up agile development try to
create an environment where the within
one team in a larger development group
the experience is nearly this
as as if you were only on a one team
project so within that one team almost
all of the agile development practices
would be would be the same and of course
if the team is distributed inside the
team which I wouldn't recommend then of
course the practices of working together
in workshops become a lot harder but
it's it's the distribution in that sense
is harder than the skill the other way
around there are a couple of practices
which are which I consider to be the the
most important practices to pay
attention to them when scaling agile
development the first one is continuous
integration continuous integration both
the continuously integrating and having
a continuous integration system with
lots of automated tests and it provides
the basis for multiple teams to work on
the on the same code base and therefore
I consider continuous integration deaky
practice that an organization needs to
work on when they start scaling at your
development and then at the same time or
after then the practice of feature teams
so restructuring your organization so
that the teams are structured around
customer centric features rather than
subsystems or components of the of the
architecture enables the teams to work
much more independent and it reduces the
planning and coordination needs between
the teams so convenience integration
together with feature teams I consider
to be the key practices when scaling up
agile development very
very interesting so I actually had very
similar experiences in the company that
I worked for when we did our HL
transition and it's nice to to get it
confirming from the de master basically
very nice so what are the main
impediments in large organizations for
getting HL a forgetting edge um there's
an an enormous amount of impediments in
large organizations and we me incorrect
actually published an article related to
that culty the top ten impediments for
agile development
so I recommend looking at that for more
information so the main the main
impediments are for example traditional
functional organizations focus on
individual performance rather than on
team performance and everything
structured around individual
responsibility versus team's
responsibility not very developed
development practices because most large
organizations don't train their
developers very well instead they assume
that universities did that which is a
wrong assumption very localized silos
local optimization thinking such as
distributing your development and then
and then saving on travel cost which of
course shows well on the D balance sheet
but it will lower your productivity
significantly but that one is not
measured so they will never know and so
all these kind of things it's usually in
large organizations you are not short of
impediments
and it will take a long time for them to
to be resolved it will probably take
forever to get them all resolved you
mentioned that there is a distinction
between distributed software development
and scaling software development and
that doing distributed software
development is harder dand and only
scaling to a large software development
team so where's a limit where you say
well now this the distribution corrupts
my software development and it's not
feasible anymore to produce anyway
in any case software efficiently I
usually would recommend against any type
of distribution having all people
located in the same location I say
almost per definition creates the most
efficient development now I'm not saying
that I've worked on projects which are
co-located because have have never
worked on a project it is large and
co-located in one building all all large
products I've worked on or has seen art
by definition distributed and it's it's
more how do you deal with that and if
you have distribution I the first thing
I would recommend is to try to avoid
distribution within the teams but have
instead distribution between teams so
that inside one team all the people are
co-located and they can sit in a team
room and etc etc etc but that there is
different teams working from different
sites it's it's still painful but it's
slightly less painful than distribution
inside the team and then try to avoid as
much having teams in in different time
zones because that just makes the
synchronization between the teams
very painful like I work here in
Singapore and we worked at a small
project where they had people in
Singapore and people in New York and
it's a 12-hour time zone difference and
those are just very very painful to try
to deal with them now one of the
problems with the recommendation I just
gave to try to get the distribution
between teams rather than inside teams
is that once you work within traditional
development group then usually they're
structured around the the architecture
still so they have component teams and
if they are then distributed then the
distribution also is according to their
architecture so if you would switch from
component teams to feature teams in that
organization then either one of the
sites will need to learn a lot about the
the technology or the components that he
other site has been specializing in all
you need to do distribution within the
team so there's no easy way to resolve
that problem when making the switch from
component to feature teams I see and I
think you have probably experienced that
yourself I'm experiencing that myself
since three years and I'm continue to
experience it for the next years it's a
painful process yeah so at least now we
do recommend to to do it always to a
gradual feature team adoption and not
change over everything it won't because
that is just for well it works but you
get all the pain at once and it
sometimes leads to even people quitting
but doing a gradual transition works
pretty well and then you might for
example in the beginning temporarily
have a team that is distributed within
the team but then for the main purpose
of
trying to get the knowledge distributed
better over the site's awesome but on a
longer run I wouldn't try to avoid that
kind of teams especially and people take
time we humans take time to learn to
accept to move on to make things happen
to do the transition absolutely
I realize initially I thought it would
take weeks but then I soon realized it
will take months it will take years till
such a transition from a traditional
software process to a lean software
process actually yeah easily we're
working with organizations I one of the
first things I tell them is that at
first that it will take a long time and
second that they shouldn't be thinking
about when it's finished but they should
just consider it as an never ending
thing it might be hard to accept by
managers that it's never-ending well
everything has an ending everything is
packed into a project so there's
typically an transition project but if
something has no end it's by definition
no project anymore exactly and it's fun
to try to convince management in about
such things in one of their first
meetings which there will be so much
different assumptions that it's it's
hard to even have an conversation so
what is your experience with that do you
like to share some insights on how to
convince management well I I don't think
I have I have much insight such as you
already said people many most managers
or in fact all of them at least the ones
I know they they are people and people
take take time to learn so I don't if I
if I meet with management of an
organization I don't
the illusion that I can just say X and
then they're convinced and realizing
what they're starting so the learning is
just gradual and what I do typically is
try to as early on explain that the kind
of huge differences or that the huge
changes they take annex can expect and I
think usually that's not believed it's
like one organization I said that within
their organization it's probably going
to take 10 to 20 years to make make some
serious progress on this and the answer
was no we have an execution culture we
can do this in one year and then then I
just said okay oh I'd be impressed to
see that I think they're now in their
fourth year
do I need to consider something and my
software design to make dispersed teams
work with the on the product so they get
the background of the question a bit and
in traditional development typically
architects or the architecture tries to
freeze interfaces and one of the reasons
for fixing interfaces is that the
software interfaces become the
communication channels between the teams
because the teams map to the software
etc one of the difficult changes from
from architecture perspective is that if
you move towards feature teams than the
the component chain or the interface
changes should almost always be inside
the team inside the one team which is
implementing the feature and because of
them there is usually not much benefits
for freezing the interface
our fixing the interfaces because the
software interfaces are no longer the
communication channels between the teams
and this is this is actually one of the
hardest changes in some of the products
I worked with because they are so used
to having to fix the interfaces that
they have this huge interface changed
process and interface repositories and
things like that into place which which
actually makes it really really hard to
change the interface so even if the
interface is only within a certain team
then the infrastructure they set up
around their interfaces make it
impossible to change it even though from
the programming language perspective it
would be simply adding a parameter or
something like them
so no normally there's not much need to
change the to fix the interfaces anymore
how do you deal with consistency
consistency in design consistency in the
architecture of the software piece the
team's are producing do you allow
dedicated roles like architects in the
in the setup well allow Elise of course
the the the wrong verb there because
usually I don't think I ever have the
authority to say or disallow any way I
understand the question let me think
about how to frame that I'll start with
the the roles I do think architectural
specialization is useful and with
architectural specialization I mean
people who specialize in trying to have
an overview and trying to figure out
what it tough are
actual decisions or questions are within
their system I don't see much use of
assigning of role to that person because
often when you when you create a role it
also limits the type of work that such a
person does and I would definitely not
recommend too hefty architects out
working outside of the teams so a person
with an architectural specialization
would be a person inside the team who
has a big interest in looking at the
overall and looking at architectural
decisions now sometimes in organizations
there's there has been so much
specialization that the persons can
focus on architectural decisions are are
very rare there's only a few of them and
then product groups often make the
argument that they don't want to put
that person inside a team because that
would that would limit their usage so
one of the practices we or one of the
experiments we recommend in in our
second book is to try out something
which we call travelers and travelers
are people who you basically set free so
you you have a group of people who are
technically incredibly good or have a
good overview good history of the system
and every iteration you let them decide
which team they join and I joined one
team dedicated for an iteration and then
after that they go where their knowledge
is most needed so they look for another
team and they join that other team and
the
join the team of course their their main
purpose is to share their specialization
their specialized knowledge with the
rest of the team so that the
organization becomes less dependent on
their specialized knowledge and we've
done that bit with some some product and
it was it was quite interesting there
was a group of six people who were the
most technical capable persons in the
product and four of them actually
decided to just stay with one team and
never changed to another team and to
enjoyed their role of jumping from one
team to the other team and next to that
it is useful to have informal groups
such as which are sometimes called
community of practice which are
volunteering groups of people with
similar interests who get together to
talk about that similar interest and
that is definitely one there should be
definitely one related to architecture
where these people inside the team will
specialize on architecture they can join
this informal community of people talk
about it and try to make architectural
decisions still that's the interesting
and and also on confirming because in
our HR transition we have now also build
up community of practice for the
architectural specialization but also
for other disciplines like testing like
for scrum masters I guess this is also
one of the recommendations in your book
to install communities of practice that
then hold together the large set up
again right absolutely if you move to
cross-functional self-managing teams and
you
abandon the traditional matrix
organization so that there is a very
clear team responsibility then some of
the functional specialization might get
lost and putting an informal
volunteering organization such as
communities of practice over the formal
organization to to not forget the focus
on functional specialization also is
really important what are your key
takeaways after all those years of
consulting and coaching large HL
software development organizations well
I don't think I have key takeaways in
the sense that if you would ask me the
same question tomorrow you would
probably get a different answer but I'll
just mention what's what's on my mind
now and some of the things that that we
have used when when working on an agile
transition one of one of my my rules for
for organizing my work and my time is
always to work with people who are
interested and do not work with people
who are not interested and it I don't
sometimes I say ignore them but it's not
necessarily what I mean
what I mean by that is that often in a
transition there's a lot of effort going
into convincing people who are just not
ready to be convinced and it's it's it's
often more useful to take the people who
are interested and ready and work with
them and use their enthusiasm to to
create results and then let the people
were not interested or not ready yet let
them learn at their own speed so give
them the space for them to learn rather
than push
kingdom around all the time it is what I
often see happening in in transitions so
that would be one take away you work
with large projects you support
organizational change yet you still
develop for example you're the author of
the open source unit test framework CPP
you test it is a rare combination to
keep developing why do you do that yeah
so CPP you test this and project I work
on together with James grinning just to
promote his upcoming work a bit James
one of t as your manifesto Sinese has
book coming up called TDD in in C for
embedded systems and many large products
are embedded system so and many large
products you see so then you probably
want to pick up his book which should be
out in November but it wasn't a question
my favorite role in a large product is
to work on the lowest level and the
highest level and try to not work to
maturity levels in between and the
lowest level I mean that work on code so
actually pair up with developers look at
their code base look at their practices
on on development level and the highest
I mean and the people running the whole
product and the typically two three
layers of management in between I tend
to work a little bit less with or prefer
that also so that there's an undirected
link between the developers and and the
people trying to make the organizational
change decisions and I I do that because
in my opinion almost all problems that
an organization has are visible they are
right there
in their code just nobody is looking so
if you look at their codebase any any
problems or any impediments with them
within their organizations will be
visible in their codebase so looking at
their code test gives an enormous amount
of input in what the what the actual
impediments are in the organization and
what the focus points need to be and I
consider that important because in I
worked in large organizations for a long
time and there's often managers creating
work for each other where they're saying
this is an impediment and you need to
solve it and then they have meetings and
then they track it etcetera but when you
go to the lowest level if you go to the
development level if you go to the code
level often the the things they are
working on are just not relevant on that
level so staying close to code usually
keeps me real it keeps me focused on on
the things that we'll have that that
impact the day to day life of the people
who are creating the product and I think
that is very important and I try to
avoid specialising only in development
or only in organizational advice or only
in even only in agile development and
and try to keep broad because keeping
broad also helps you see the overview
and makes you give different advice that
was a very nice pearl of wisdom actually
and we're coming to the end of our show
do you have something you like to share
with our listeners well we we already
shared quite a lot I guess
so then it's fine and we use that last
pearl of do to really stay connected
across all levels of hierarchy
especially connect the topmost with
actual implementation level as the final
word so I would like to thank you pass
that was very interesting and hope to
talk to you soon and in real person in
real life meeting somewhere at some
place will be soon unless you go to Asia
as you know I don't nowadays I rarely
leave leave Asia okay then I say bye-bye
well maybe in the next agile conference
if you're going to be there I'll try to
so thanks for for the recording for
taking the time bye bye best
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio si radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and the
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SA radio team via
the website or you can advertise for su
radio for example by clicking on the
dick reddit delicious and slashed up
buttons or by talking about us on
Twitter and Facebook you can also
support us by joining team and
shouldering some of the work to contact
the team please send email to team at se
- radio net or if your feedback is
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under a
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details
[Music]
you